Everything is spaghetti method.
Watch your breath.
It's a little harder in the evening. You
get tired.
Food doesn't help.
Try to
tie the mind to the breath and sort of
relax into it.
It's a quiet place in this quiet
evening. Just relax into the breath.
Go to the golden room.
One
golden sunlight
illuminating the room.
Like gold, like the good gold.
Just one thing.
Golden room.
Outside the window
sky
Up the upper half of the window over the
sky. Lower half filled with mountains.
your heart teacher, whoever that may be.
Seated in front of you.
What?
Focus on your teacher's face.
And then upon your eyes.
Now I'd like to try something. Make your
eyes very small.
Imagine that somehow your eyes are very
far away.
Very, very small.
You sort of have to concentrate to
look there
to keep your mind on
very small, beautiful, loving eye.
Look at the action.
Hold it.
We'll hold it for a few minutes. Observe
how your mind starts to get tired.
And the quality
of the
holding starts to degrade over a few
minutes time. So, you're watching this
model.
He just had a big pasta dinner.
He's tired from yesterday and today.
Observe how
quality of the
the eyes starts to degrade and you start
to get tired.
So like that.
Okay, yeah.
So I'll do a little bit of posture.
Okay.
All right.
So the second uh
first meditation problem was what?
Laylo.
And then you overcame it with the effort
of thinking about so uh shindam, which
means uh
think about how cool meditation is.
Which will automatically want lead you
to want it.
Which will automatically lead you to do
something.
Which will automatically lead you to get
better at it. That's basically the
the the flow.
Uh
which will get you to send jopa really,
you see? Then that'll get you to sit
down and try to meditate, okay?
Which will get you to the down here.
To the start, okay? So far we just got
to the start. I taught this in uh
Taipei, we only got
to about here.
Uh
but hopefully we get further than that.
What's the second problem? What's the
second classical problem encountered by
anyone who tries to meditate?
Yes, called damnam jepa. Say damnam.
Damnam.
Jepa.
Damnam means the instructions
uh
that you got from your teacher. Jepa
means
forget, okay? You forget the
instruction.
But as you know, those of you studied
it, it has a more particular meaning
which is
uh you lose the object completely, okay?
So you go from the sun-filled room to
the project you have to do when you get
back
next week, okay? You just drop the
object completely. You're you're off the
object.
Okay?
And then you have to use the iron chain,
okay? What's in his left hand?
Chamber.
Bringing the mind back to the object,
okay?
And it's no coincidence that it's an
iron chain.
Okay? So it's like
really hard. You have to pull it back,
okay? Pull the mind back to the object
that you were supposed to be imagining,
okay?
Personally Personally I find an
elliptical orbit is useful.
My mind is headed off towards uh
next week's project, you know? And And
you can
try to jump, you know, iron hook and
chain. You can try to pull it back
diametrically.
And somehow it doesn't work for me. I
like to build up some momentum and
like a frisbee and let it let it like a
boomerang, let it come around, come
back. So I don't try to fight it
like this. I'm like
Oh yeah, we have that project next week.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, that project. We
We can work on this. Yeah, we got to do
that and that and that. Yeah, yeah.
And uh to do that
we're going to have to sit down. Yeah,
then we have to finish up this week.
Yeah, and then to finish up this week we
have to finish up the first few days and
means I'm going to have to be coming
back to the session I'm on.
And then maybe
Where is that golden room? You see
I bring it around.
I like to bring it around on its own
impetus
and let it come back like a like
swinging a a chain and then it flies
back rather than
uh trying to fight the tendency. Make it
part of your distraction.
Check the distraction.
Yeah, we should think about next week.
To get there, we got to think about the
end of this week. To get there, we got
to start here.
And then, you know, instead of saying
come back, come back, okay? Like that.
Try it. It's interesting. So, that's
timber.
Uh
Which is what? Is that the
fifth antidote?
Okay. So, the fix for uh
the fix for the second meditation
problem is the fifth antidote because we
had three extra antidotes
for lay long
because we had one thing trying and
getting good at it.
Okay? Got it? You got it? All right.
Uh
Which leads me I think I'll go to
I can never mix you up.
Uh how do you get here? Which power gets
you here?
Which power gets you to start
meditating?
Yeah, tip of shruti, listening.
Listening They don't even have it on the
chart.
Okay, I don't think so.
Uh
before you get to this first number one,
you have to go to a class and the
teacher teaches about meditation and
and then you know what to do and you
know how to sit down and things like
that. Okay, so get to the sitting down,
you have to go to a class and the first
master explains you how to meditate,
okay?
So, that's the first of the six
powers is is
is hearing, meaning learning, okay?
Uh
Then you get to This is given to Jampa,
okay? Up here.
Number nine.
It'll probably say nine, too, down here
at the bottom, but
nine meaning it's the ninth It's the
ninth picture.
Two meaning it's the second of the ninth
states.
It says, "Keeping the mind on the object
with brief continuity." Okay?
So, you don't get to the second state
of meditation till you get to the first
bend in the road on the left. Do you
want to show these guys?
Over there?
Okay. So, it's
This is uh
Where is it?
Number two is way up here. All right?
Where you've got some brief continuity
by here. By the time you get here,
you have some flow on the object. Okay?
You're able to hold it for brief periods
of time.
They are still less than the time
off the object, okay? It's not bad,
okay? It's progress.
This was the fly on the cow pie
down here.
And then by a By the time you're up
here, you've got some continuity on the
object, okay?
Let's see what Chögyam Trungpa Rinpoche
chose to put between those two.
Uh this chart was designed by Chögyam
Trungpa Rinpoche,
who was the student of Kunga Drolchok
Rinpoche.
And he's the tutor of the current Dalai
Lama, okay? So, and the And my teacher's
teacher.
So,
let's see what he's chosen to put on the
on the chart.
Here's uh
Number two was the chain
for either pulling back directly or
swinging back, okay?
And now we have to talk about this uh
hook.
I forget the In In Tibetan, it's called
chakyu. Say chakyu.
Chakyu.
So, chakyu can mean any kind of hook.
Uh
like a fishing hook,
or a
Sometimes they say "Jinda la chaggi
sha."
Say "Jinda."
Jinda.
La.
Chaggi.
Sha.
Set the hook on a sponsor for the
monastery.
That's a common use of chaggi here in a
Uh
Kind of funny.
Um
What is a chaggi?
Yeah, that little curly
hook-like vowel under the Tibetan
letter.
It's called That's a u sound.
And it's called a foot hook. Chaggi. So,
gi means hook. So, this is a chaggi. Cha
means iron or steel.
So, chaggi.
He's got a chaggi in his right hand.
He's got a chain in his in his left
hand, okay? So, the right hand is
chaggi. It's a hook. And on an elephant,
I believe you hook it under the ear.
And their skin is so thick that you have
to really pull for them to even feel it.
They don't even feel it. But, you
you have to jam it really hard into
their ear like an inch or two before
they even feel it cuz their skin is so
thick.
So, and the and the ear is sensitive.
So, you
to turn the
to turn the elephant, or to get its
attention,
you you jam the chaggi into the ear,
okay?
Uh in our case in meditation, chaggi
refers to shishin. Say "Shishin."
Shishin.
It's like shishin. Shishin means
It's like thank you. Uh shishin means uh
Well, how do we translate it? What's
number two say?
Awareness. Okay, we'll call it
awareness.
Uh we talked about it in Phoenix, but
those of you who weren't there
Shishin is described in the scripture
as
setting aside a corner of your mind to
watch the rest of your mind as it
meditates, okay? Setting aside a corner
of your mind
to watch the rest of your mind
as it meditates. So,
uh shashin, for example,
might be used to It's a detector.
It's like a smoke alarm.
Okay, I like to compare it to a smoke
alarm.
So, the the function of a smoke alarm
is not to put out a fire, right?
It's simply to alert you to the fact
that there is a fire, okay? So,
shashin's job
is not to do anything except set off an
alarm
that what? In in this case?
You're off the object.
So, shashin
detects
that you haven't thought about the
golden room for about 5 minutes.
Okay? Like, if you have a slow shashin,
you know?
So, hopefully you develop your shashin,
you know? Hopefully you make it
more sensitive.
You know, there's more sensitive smoke
detectors and less sensitive smoke
detectors. So,
hopefully you develop your shashin
strong enough
that it can alert you that you're no
longer on the object, okay? For me, I
don't know about you, it's just kind of
a coincidence that I notice that I'm off
the object
and uh
I wander back onto it
kind of by accident and then go off the
other way.
So, anyway, shashin's job is to detect
that you are not on the object, okay?
Usually, it can detect other things that
we'll talk about. But, at this point,
he's got
shashin. Which do you think goes first?
The left chain or the right hook?
Yeah, the hook is used first, right?
First the alarm goes off
and then the
chamber's the the left hand, the chain
is like what the water sprinkler thing
that goes off. The smoke alarm sets off
the water sprinkler. So,
the detector is shushing. Detector is
like, "Oh, I'm off the object." And then
chamber kicks in and pulls you back to
the object, okay? So, you wouldn't have
a pull back without a alarm.
There has to be an alarm go off in your
mind that says, "We're not on the object
anymore."
And then you have to coax or beat or
fight or battle or
trick the mind back to the object, okay?
And that's chamber, all right?
Uh we're calling the object or bringing
them
bringing the mind back to the object.
I'm going to go through the other
numbers up to
uh Ginde Chopel's slight continuity,
right? And let's see what he chose to
put in there. I I'm not uh
It'll be a little different than the
text, but let's see. Okay. He also
edited this text.
This was a transcript.
This was a recording
taken on, you know, rice paper.
Uh and then it took him I think it took
him close to 20 years
to edit it. He worked on it steadily for
20 years, something like that.
And and the day it came out it was a
classic. It was carved the day it came
out, which is very unusual.
And uh so anyway,
the since he did both, they should match
pretty well.
So, we got number one is
putting the mind into meditation. Number
two is
uh
bringing the mind back. Number three is
the alarm.
And then number four is let me see here.
Lam tu kup pa tuk tok tu.
The six
bends in this path
the six bends in the road represent that
six paths.
Okay?
Two.
Dullness.
January there.
I've got two different also. Yeah, two
different also. It's very The card is
not very clear, okay?
Two different also means the first one
is
What is that?
Two different also.
The first power is
self-learning, listening, okay?
Due to the first
power, you are able to attain the first
of the nine levels, okay? You are able
to attain the first of the nine levels.
That's what he said under the elephant,
okay?
That's what note number four says.
Number five.
Long ball sand.
Long ball means elephant. So, what's
that say?
The elephant is your mind.
Long ball sand.
And then this is where this whole chart
takes off. From there was an ancient
scripture that said the mind is like an
elephant tied to the stake of your
of your meditation object with your
camera
and session, okay?
That that
So, this note says
the elephant is your mind and the color
black on the elephant represents chin
wet.
Which is what? Chin wet sand means
represents chin wet.
Dullness, okay?
Dullness. We were exploring dullness at
the end of that last meditation.
Not really. And that's what you have to
do. We had a a meditation program what?
15 years ago in Connecticut and
we purposely overfed everyone.
And we fed them very bad food.
It was a big plot. We we planned it for
weeks
in Nancy Karen's living room.
And we had the perfect person to
What do you call it?
Execute the plan.
Who loved pizza.
And so we overfed everybody on pizza and
then we took them in the room and we
meditated. And everybody got chihua.
Okay? So, chihua means like
very gross sort of dullness of the mind.
Sleepiness of the mind.
It can be brought on by not getting
enough sleep.
By traveling long distances just before
a meditation retreat.
By working on cabins for 3 months before
uh
you can get it by overeating. Okay?
These are ways to get
dullness.
Uh let's keep going on the chart.
I want you to know the chart so you can
use it at home.
Uh
tell
towa dung
khado nagpo gopa tsun. Okay? Say tell.
khado
nagpo
gopa tsun
Uh
tell is the literary form form of do
which means what?
Yeah, in in the colloquial the rata
drops off
and it becomes
eu.
Which means monkey. Okay? But the
the medium form is do and the ancient
form is ta. Okay? So, ta means monkey.
Uh towa
towa means
How did I translate it? What's number
six there?
Say again.
It means to stand.
distraction.
Okay.
Yeah.
Okay, so that
the monkey represents distraction and
the black color of the monkey represents
agitation.
What's the distinction between
distraction
and and agitation? That's what we need
to talk about, okay?
Not all distractions are agitation,
okay? Not all distractions are
agitation, guppa.
Because guppa is defined as a special
kind of
distraction, which is
towards a pleasant object, okay?
So,
90%
of all distraction from the object as
opposed to sleepiness,
okay? Sleepiness is just a degrading of
the quality of the state of mind.
Uh distraction is where your mind is
flies. The word towa means uh
to fly off, like usetta, usetta in the
sadhana.
Uh
mind flies off into the 10 directions,
towa.
So,
towa means for the mind to
fly away from the ob-
from
the attention to fly away from the
object in the way that light would be
scattered. Scattered, you could say
scattered is not bad, okay?
But not all scattering
is towards a desirable object, you see?
Why? There are two other classic types
of objects, okay? Which are
Say again?
Things you don't like.
Yeah, things and people, usually people
you don't like. Or it could be you could
towa towards the coldness of your room.
You see? You could You could start
getting distracted by
thoughts about how miserable your room
is
and how cold you feel in your room.
Okay, that would be towa but not guppa.
That would be distraction but not what
we call agitation because agitation is
classically aimed at a desirable thing,
okay?
So, the the the monkey represents all
kinds of distraction. The blackness of
the monkey represents distraction
towards a desirable object, which
accounts for 95% of
distraction. And that's the point. In
the scripture, they say
we concentrate on agitation or
attraction towards a desirable object
because that's 95% of your distraction,
okay?
Which would include planning
for the next day or the next week or the
next life,
okay? So, planning is maybe a very
common distraction, right? Food is a
very common distraction. Sex is a very
common distraction.
Uh
things you want to buy or things you
want to do
is a very common distraction. Uh
He cites memories of
classical folk dances performances,
which nowadays would be
television or movies.
I think movies, okay?
Remembering movies,
music,
music, you know, a song running through
your head. We were talking about doing
music tonight, and we decided
it'd probably be in your head for 8
days, and
you wouldn't want Frosty the Snowman in
your head for 8 days.
Uh
So, uh
So,
those are That's the most classical form
of
distraction is towards nice things.
What's a What's an another
We got nice things, terrible things.
Then they say virtuous things, okay?
They make a separate classification
about distraction
in the form of thinking about something
nice that you have to do, like a Dharma
project, okay?
Like the Spanish mission
sanctuary
adobe
with arches and Spanish tiles and
gardens and lawns and a full regulation
soccer field.
Now, to attract the the Spanish American
population.
Seriously. And basketball courts and
somebody throwing a small cafe
uh
with internet.
Uh
All right.
All right. All right.
That's another half acre you got to pay.
Okay. So, anyway, these are good things
to talk about but not while you're
meditating on the golden
Okay?
That's the third kind of distraction.
Okay? Like it's a nice It's a virtuous
thing. It's a It's a holy thing.
But in meditation
a holy thing that's not your object
becomes an evil thing. Okay?
It's wrong to think of a virtuous
project. It's destructive
during a meditation because you're
supposed to have only one object. And
that's the golden rule. And that's not a
basketball court.
Okay? All right. So, that's an
interesting distinction to make.
But the black color of the monkey
means It's The reason they chose to make
the monkey all black
was that
distraction towards things you'd like.
Especially plans and
and girls and movies and music and other
things that you enjoy.
These are the two great uh
These are the two great classic enemies
of meditation. Okay? And all meditation
consists of threading a middle way
between these two ditches.
We We came down We took a different road
here, okay? Which was more icy and snow
covered. We didn't make it. Uh
We were up on We got like halfway down
the hill and we just We went off the
road like four times. And then uh
we decided just just We just got to get
out and call somebody. So, we got out
and called somebody. Then this guy shows
up.
And he said, "I can drive your car down
for you." And we're like, "That no
thanks."
And he said,
"You know those big snow drifts off to
the side?" And we said, "Yeah." He said,
"They are covering very deep dangerous
ditches." You know? And we're like,
"Okay.
Uh we'll just wait for the tow truck."
You know? So,
meditation is the same, okay? On one
side is uh
dullness.
The deep ditch of dullness.
And then on the other side is uh
attraction towards something nice that
you want to think about, like food.
And then your meditation means driving
down that slick road and trying not to
slide off the You know what I mean? You
see what I mean? That's meditation. And
it's a constant
correction of the wheel. And we were
talking about it in Phoenix. If you
watch a person drive, even a bad driver,
uh
they are constantly correcting. A new
driver, totally new driver, first day
they ever drove, they go like this.
And they never They don't come back, you
know? And then you grab the wheel, you
know? We had a monk in in India. We were
trying to teach him to drive. And then
every time he
he looked out the window, he'd go like
this.
It was really scary. Uh
But an an experienced driver, there's
this constant What do you call it? Um
Unconscious.
Unconscious correction process. They
They can talk on their phone and they
can be fooling with the radio or
fighting with their wife.
And the hands are still
moving back and forth. So, what we see
is a state of meditation where the
corrections are are constant.
And and you're not even aware of it. You
see, you are you are constantly
correcting. And we'll talk about it, you
know.
There will be a tendency to get dull.
And then you will you will do certain
internal practices within your mind
to to to to stoke it up a bit,
to raise the level of the mind,
which means turning to the right, right?
Then that will go too far.
And you will start thinking about lunch.
And then you'll do another practice to
bring the mind down a little bit, like
think about death
for a minute. And then you'll get the
mind too depressed, and you'll get
sleepy. And then you'll have to bring it
up again. And then there's this constant
uh correcting to avoid these two classic
problems of meditation. Okay, these are
the two
classic problems. We we will try to
spend this week exploring those two
problems, okay?
All right. Uh verse number seven
is
Dina Semde Gyumba Khar.
Mencha Yulmedan
Chaychungi Kyebar
Gopa Me
Tayshyi Betsal Tokshuk Kyay Chaychungi
Kyeparol.
So, you see here uh
he's in the first bend of the road,
you can see a a fire.
Uh it's called uh flames What do you
call it? Flames of tons of flame.
And the Tibetan says tons of flame.
So, here
this represents
this first big fire here
represents the intensity or the power
that you need to assert
in these two corrective measures.
Uh
the alarm line
and the pullback line. Okay, so at this
point in your meditative practice
the corrections are gross.
You know?
And they're muscle. The corrections are
muscled. Like they're
Just people do yoga that way, right?
They muscle through it.
And it everything's a
What do you call it? Abrupt. The
movements are abrupt and
and they're muscling instead of like
gliding, you know? And it it's probably
a necessary thing to get to the gliding.
But for your first 6 months of yoga,
you're muscling everything. So, this
great fire
represents the fact that at this point
the corrective process is is a struggle.
And the the corrections are big and
blatant and
overdone. Okay? It's like rip.
And then you're going off the road
before you rip.
You know, what do you call it? You you
crank it.
Like that. Okay, so that's what And then
he says down here he says you'll notice
that as we proceed along the path
the flames get smaller and smaller.
And then suddenly they're all gone.
Okay?
Which means
by level eight
okay?
It becomes effortless. Okay? The
correction process is
is automatic. You are
driving and talking on your cell phone
and you don't notice your hands moving.
It's a it's a on autopilot. What do you
call that thing that you like to do?
Cruise control.
Cruise control. Okay?
It's a cruise control.
So, the when the flames finally gets
They get smaller and smaller, less
effort expended in correction until
beyond this point there's no flames.
Okay, there's no effort. The correction
process becomes
unconscious. All right?
I mean
hopefully you're not unconscious.
Yeah, of course.
Let's check. Let's do some more
meditation.
As as the day proceeds
on a typical retreat
for most people and it's not always the
same for everybody.
But normally you should shorten the
the length of each session
as you go through the day. So
the last session
in a long retreat in the last session in
the evening might be
5 minutes.
Even for a very experienced person.
Okay? A nice 5-minute
intense meditation.
I I I I'll tell you I'm I'm guessing
something, okay?
You guys are thinking when is he going
to do the real meditation? You know? No,
you're thinking that. You're thinking is
he going to get to a half an hour or is
he going to get to an hour? Are we just
going to
is this just some kind of warm-up?
And I say no. This is a this is an
ancient
alternative method of meditating where
you just keep going back
for 5 minutes, 10 minutes like 18 times
throughout the day. And check it out and
see if you want to try to do it for a
couple months or a year or something.
Instead of trying to sit there for a
half hour or an hour
do a bunch of small sessions. What
you'll discover
is a
is a tendency towards continuity across
the sessions.
Okay? If you do an hour at 9:00 on
Tuesday and then do an hour
at 9:00 on Wednesday
you don't get this feeling of coming
back to a place where you've been.
You get the feeling of like starting
over, okay?
So, check it out. This method makes you
feel like you're meditating all day and
taking breaks
for meals. You see?
You feel like you've been in the golden
room.
You're coming back to a place that you
just went to the bathroom and you came
back to the golden room. You see what I
mean?
And you'll feel a continuity across the
sessions, which is very desirable.
Then you get some kind of intense
progress coming. So, try it. Just check
it out. I I know it's not what everybody
does,
but it is a tradition.
And uh
What's cool is that the quality of the
meditation doesn't degrade.
Uh if you try an hour or even a half
hour, it will degrade. I don't know
anyone who can sustain an hour.
I know lots of people who sit for an
hour.
Uh but I I honestly don't know anyone
who can sustain an hour's meditation.
So, try
uh rather than fighting to get to go for
an hour,
try
uh three or four sessions during the day
and space them out and see how see how
you like it. Just try it. You see how
you like it. So, here we go.
They should get shorter as the day goes
on.
Go back to your breath, very, very
silent.
You can't unzip your jacket. You can't
shift your body.
You can't even sniffle
if you're focused only on your breath.
Come to the garden room.
Small room.
Windows on several sides and
golden light. Make it Try to make it a
I don't know how to describe it. Like a
a darker gold.
A warm gold. Like a molten gold. Okay?
That kind of light is bathing the room.
Like a
the last light of the day. Golden.
Outside the window and then
blue sky
on the upper half of the window and
mountain on the lower half of the
window.
And then I must sit in front of you.
And then they reach out and take your
hand. So, in your lap,
you're holding your mama's hands. And
that's all. Just focus on the hands
until we stop.
We're just focusing
on the touch of their hand on your hand.
Stay there.
You don't need to do anything.
There's no discussion going on. No one's
going to move.
Just stay there with their hand on your
hand.
Stay there in the feeling of that.
You have nothing else to do tonight.
Constantly mind back to the object,
detect it leaving the object.
Notice which kinds of distractions you
tend to have.
Your cherished project,
someone who hurt you,
or something you want, food,
movie, music.
Okay, 2 more minutes.
Try really hard to keep your mind on the
hands.
Relax. Slowly come back.
There's a very uh
Vorkurve teaches very insistent that you
should end the meditation while it's
going well.
Okay? So,
you should end the meditation feeling
like you you would have liked to have
stayed a little longer.
Okay? That's a trick of the trade.
Used to have a gold miner, like an old
old pioneer man gold miner
in our Boy Scout trip, but he was 120 or
something.
And his his name was Mr. Craig, but we
called him Fud.
And he'd say, "Tricks of the trade,
boys."
And then he'd teach us some incredible
knot or something that you could use to
for backpack and
like that you used for mules to carry
gold and
So, I like tricks of the trade. So, one
of the tricks of the trade is
uh
stop while it's good, okay?
Like
and it's hard to do cuz you want to suck
some more out of it, but
start and then you want to go back.
You'll feel happy to go back, okay?
I thought I'd take questions for a
couple of minutes and then uh
let you go early then maybe 9:30.
And uh I'll take questions for a while
and then uh I thought to send you to bed
with a little bit of emptiness dessert.
All right. So, we would do like 10
minutes out of the
a few minutes more of emptiness, but but
I thought if you have any questions,
yeah.
What if um
your mind is racing but not toward
something uh
like
if if you have uh restlessness,
you can just like lift the arms there.
Cuz your mind is still happy and
quieting down
instead of something
like getting upset. But if you're
restless because of something I'm happy
that I stopped very depressed and that I
this meditation on that is
beginning to work.
Yeah, yeah, okay.
Uh
So, we're getting into the subject of
the
These are beautiful It's a beautiful
question and it's a beautiful art
or a skill
of
what do you do if you if you have a an
extreme form of either one of the
elephant and the monkey, right?
What if you have an extreme form of
agitation? You start thinking about
something you want or you have the
opposite problem, right?
And suppose your agitation has been
triggered by already depressed thoughts.
And and you're telling me to bring my
mind down further.
Uh what do you want me to do about that?
So,
antidotes
within the mind are divided into three
kinds. Like I can say I mean it's not
formally presented that way, but you can
derive that.
One means uh
with a little bit of uh
without leaving the object, you can
bring the level of the mind up or down
very gently without leaving the object.
It requires a partial leaving of the
object, I guess.
But you don't let go of the object. So
you're still holding the object, but you
are consciously trying to raise the
mind or lower the mind. Okay? If the
mind is too depressed or the mind is too
agitated, okay?
With the other is where without opening
your eyes
you drop the object for a while
and you go to another
brief meditation which will raise or
lower the mind.
And then drastic means are uh
you open your eyes and you throw water
on your face, okay?
No, there is such a thing. You don't
break your
filter, you don't break your uh
your meditation posture
but you open your eyes and you look
around and you slap yourself and you
look at how much time you got left and
you know, those are really drastic. So
uh
But
I think what's interesting for all of us
is what are the sort of subtle
sub-meditations you can do
to raise or lower
the When I say raise or lower, I mean uh
pep up the mind or calm it down a bit
because it's too
it's getting a little dull
or it's getting a little too frisky.
Okay? Like how do you keep it It's like
a What do you call a bump bubble soap.
How do you keep it at the right
altitude, you know?
So,
I'll give you some classic ones and then
we'll talk more about it, okay? Cuz to
me this is the most important question.
That question is the most important
question, you know?
My mind
uh keeps going to
some song or some project I have to do,
right? So, how do I bring it back? How
do I calm the mind? Bring it down a bit.
And and you are
thinking about people who died in your
life
is a good way to bring it down very
fast. It's like my brother died.
Uh I just have to think about him and
and I'm not thinking about lunch
anymore. It takes
it takes less than 10 seconds
and my mind is down, you know? So,
uh the opposite one
is uh
how to pep the mind up
is to you could just think about
something
inspiring
to you, you know? You could think about
the Dalai Lama, you could think about
uh
good things you've done in your life or
good people you've seen in your life or
inspiring things.
Uh
I I like I what do you call it? I like
the subject of Geshe Michael.
I like to I like to think about the cool
things he did in China or something and
I think this is one case where that's
healthy.
You know, you could say
that in the scripture they say think
about what a special person you are.
Okay? Like I
I'm at a meditation retreat,
you know,
I don't
you know, how many people really got the
transmission of emptiness
correctly?
Maybe one in
one in a million in this country, okay?
About it averages right now it's running
at about one in a million.
So, you are
one person out of a million who made it
here
to get that transmission, which came
directly from the greatest lama of
Tibet. He He was the num- He was ranked
number one debater out of 10,000
debaters the year he graduated. He was
number one.
You know? So, you're getting And his
teacher wrote the book.
You know? So, you're getting like a
really good transmission. And this is
the first one that's in English from
that lineage. So, you've got to be
a little special to be here.
Uh and uh
you just think about that. You think how
special you are.
And it's a good kind of special. It's
good to think about, you know? I'm
statistically,
which makes it undeniable, right? It's
not subjective, it's objective.
Out of 200 million people, I'm
I'm I'm one out of a million people who
made it here. And I'm hearing these
things.
And you've got to be super extraordinary
person just to have made it over the
road here.
Uh
you know?
You are
You're special.
You know? And you can't deny it. I mean,
the numbers are there. You can't deny
it.
Uh how many people
got here instead of on Facebook or on
watching a video tonight or
By the way, today is New Year's, right?
It's 1 1 1 1 in the morning.
Uh and in Tibet,
the first day of the year is a What do
you call it?
Is a
sign of how the year's going to go. How
you spend the first day of the year is
extremely important in the Tibetan
tradition because uh it's a sign of how
your whole life's going to go.
And especially the next year, you know?
So, it's just
So, is it kind of special that you spent
the
first day of the year,
you know, all day talking about
emptiness and meditation and
you know, being in one of the last clean
unpolluted forested areas on the whole
planet of the earth cuz I travel a lot.
I know how many places are left.
And and there's not this is like one of
the handful.
So, you know, you
you're pretty special.
And it's a special day and it ends the
special way that you spent the day and
you're going to have a special year and
a special life. So, you that already you
feel brighter, right? So, if you feel
yourself getting tired
or depressed
uh they say in the text they say just
if you made it this far you got to be
special. So, just think of that how
special you are, okay?
Then you'll get too special.
You know,
say,
yeah, I am like the only one.
You know, and then you got to
I'm the only American who's going to
die.
You
calm down a bit.
Got your mind going, you know.
Okay? And then you'll get all sad and
depressed and you say, no, but I really
it is I am, you know.
You know,
No, that's that's the gross correction
process. And then you'll get to where
you're just going like that.
And then you get to a place where your
hands don't move anymore and it's the
car straight, okay?
Any more questions?
So, what do you do when very strong
emotions come up when you think of or
Uh she said, what do you do when you get
very strong emotions coming up when
you're thinking about your meditation
object?
If it's anger
because you're meditating on the last
person who hurt you.
Uh
That's not what I meant.
I'm talking about me.
I uh
I usually do the four powers of
confession right there
before I go anywhere.
During the
what?
During the second one,
I start to consider how dangerous it was
that I had that anger.
And then I try to think about why I was
angry. And then I get angry again during
the confession.
Uh
But anyway,
uh
I I I think it's an interesting
question. In my mind, the question for
me is
if the teacher is looking at me and I'm
feeling these intense feelings of love,
then that becomes a second object.
I think it's a distraction.
Yeah, so that's very touchy.
You know, then that be then I've lost my
object.
You see? Cuz I'm concentrating on the
emotion or the love, the devotion.
Uh
And I've struggled with that question. I
think you can imbue the
eyes with love and you're okay. I don't
think you're going to have I don't think
it's a distraction. I've decided it's
not a distraction.
Uh
There's an intent I think you can have
an intense feeling of love and not lose
the eyes.
Uh so I don't think it's a problem.
I think it's physical.
If it gets physical?
Well, you know, like like crying.
Oh, like crying?
Yeah.
So I I I think it's a good thing, but
again it's one of those good things
which is a distraction, right? So
then you might want to back off the that
emotion.
I I wouldn't say try to lower the
devotion. I would say try to control the
crying.
Cuz the devotion I don't I can't imagine
that devotion could be too too much
devotion could be a problem.
I wouldn't mind
I don't think it's uh
I think you could pre-plan
a move of the object deeper into
devotion from the eyes. Something like
that.
So, I would call it not losing the
object.
Devotion is more important than holding
the eyes.
And it's still the object for me.
I I've struggled with that.
It's like counting the breath. Is one of
the breath?
You know? What am I doing? Breath one,
breath two.
I mean, it's two objects, you know? So,
yeah, you have to struggle with that. I
I think
yeah, you have to make sure the counting
doesn't become a second object. Okay?
Yeah.
Mhm. Yeah.
Um when you talk about losing the object
that you're focusing on
someone's face.
Yeah.
When you
the face becomes fuzzy.
Yeah.
But the shape is still there. It's still
love, but is that losing the object?
That's doneness.
That's chingwa. Uh
I find when you talk about for instance
the hands,
Yeah.
that was a completely different
thing when you lose that.
Yeah.
But the face is just this fuzzy.
Yeah, that gets into another question,
which is a good Let's go there.
Uh
it's an interesting fact
that you cannot have the third problem
of meditation until you're able to hold
the object.
Okay?
You cannot encounter the third problem
of meditation
until you're able to have fixation on
the object.
What is the third problem of meditation?
We've only done two. We did we did not
wanting to meditate and then we did
losing the object completely. But what's
the third The third problem of
meditation is
dullness and agitation. Okay.
It's a dual uh
problem which is kind of a contradiction
in a meditation class.
Uh
you know, it's a it's a two-pointed
needle. But uh
Yeah, it's either the mind gets too low
or the mind gets too high. Okay?
But it assumes that you're still on the
object. So what it's what you were
describing. It's the silhouette without
the face.
Or, you know, it's the hands but you're
kind of losing it.
Uh
So, those are
to to have the two to have the monkey
black monkey and the black elephant
problem, you have to be on the object.
If you're off the object, you won't have
those problems.
You can't be dull
on lunch.
Uh you see what I mean? Uh you got to be
on the object to have a
problem with the quality of the of the
object. So, what you're describing is
good.
You're describing the third problem,
which is you haven't lost the object
but the quality of the attention is is
is degraded.
And yeah.
So, what do you mean by that? If for
instance
problem of the face is I don't have a
photograph of memory, so I can't see
Yeah.
terms of the hands,
I didn't lose that, so should I choose
hands?
Yeah, okay. That's a new question. Okay?
Uh
no.
He said, I have trouble
I have the same trouble. I I have a
friend I mentioned in the last class.
I have a friend I I lived next to T
German potato for a while.
And and stupidly I didn't go over to see
him cuz I didn't want to bother him.
But uh my friends went.
And they asked him, "Could you draw a
Buddha for us to keep?" And and he just
went like this.
You know? And I I had a copy. I don't
know where it is. I had a copy of that
drawing. And it's perfect.
And he had some kind of photographic
memory of what visual memory, which I
don't have. You know, I can't draw the
face of my teacher. I've tried. I can't
do it.
You know, I I I see it and I understand
it and I get everything's good.
But I can't sit down and draw it, you
know? So, I think that's what you're
describing. Like
But the hands
What is say What's your name again?
Richard. Yeah, what Richard is saying is
that
the hands he can remember. I mean, the
touch of the hands is irrefutable.
Something very beautiful and you don't
forget the touch of someone's hands.
And I can remember the touch of my
teacher's hands. I know what they feel
like.
That I can describe perfectly. If I
could draw it, I could draw it. You see
what I mean?
And that's that's fine. So, his question
was
should I go for the object that is more
comfortable and compelling to me
or should I
fight my tendencies and try to up
improve my ability to visualize the
face?
And the text says
The text This is very interesting and
very important, I think. The text says,
"Normally, stick with something which is
very attractive to you
cuz you'll be better at it, you know?"
So, as far as the
parts of your llama
uh
In the beginning, I mean, for I'd say
all the time
choose something which is compelling to
you.
The selection of a meditation object is
a high art
and it's a very serious consideration
that you you have to go through.
Because once you pick it, you shouldn't
switch it easily.
You know, you should spend weeks or
months on the same object. So,
once you the selection should be very
What do you call
judicious. Yeah, like
select carefully
because then you should keep it for a
long time.
And and
and and the guideline in the scripture
is select something which is very
attractive to you, virtuous and
attractive.
So,
uh your lama's hands, the touch of your
lama's hands might be
a very
nice object, a good object, cuz you're
you already very attracted to that. And
And that's what they say. Of course,
there will come times
when your lama says, "I want you to do
this particular meditation on
emptiness." And it's not natural, and
it's not comfortable, and it's hard.
And then you got a knot with palm. And
then, you know, they'll say they'll give
you a meditation assignment and they'll
say, "Work on this
proof of emptiness."
And then you just have to fight and and
get there.
The objects that you fight for and
achieve turn out much sweeter than the
objects which were attractive and easy.
I I I predict, you know, uh I had that
experience
with logic.
You know, like my teacher forced me to
learn logic, and I hated it.
And uh
and now like we're doing this text, it's
the most exquisite thing in the world.
Uh but I never could have done it
without uh
like a couple of years of real struggle
of of something I wasn't attracted to at
all, you know? So,
but the text says start with something
you love.
And until you get strong in your
meditation, and then switch to objects
which are difficult
for you.
Maybe one more, and then I got to give
you a little emptiness to go to bed on.
My question is in order to focus on the
object, I often need to imagine the
person in the past experience, or having
them in a photo, something like that.
So, my question is so, is that related
to the level that I'm on, or is that a
grade of focus? Like when I lose the
object, or to bring it back, I have to
remember the experience, Um, some kind
of sense or something or something. And
wondering
if that is really focused on the object.
So, I imagine all these other things you
know that you can get out of it.
Uh, sorry, Peter. Your question, just to
make sure you I really heard it.
And I usually rephrase it in my own way
to to to twist it my own way. This is
not
debating him.
But, she wanted to know
let's say she's supposed to be
meditating on her llama's face.
And then, uh,
to make it stronger, to come back to it
stronger, she has to switch over to an
actual experience she had with her llama
to to to recapture the face, and then
bring it back to the golden moon.
So, is that a loss of Is that okay as a
method? I think it's great. I think
that's a redirection thing, rather than
a fighting thing. So, you you go to an
experience that you enjoyed with them.
And that's Or, she even mentioned a
photograph that she particularly enjoyed
of them. So, that I do that sometimes.
I keep a photograph in my six-times
book, which we have to do.
Uh,
that would be a virtuous distraction.
so, you
Yeah, definitely. Go to a pleasant
experience you had with them. Cat- What
do you call it? What do you do on a
computer when you
used to push F something, and you
captured the
screen capture. Do a screen capture.
Go to their face in a pleasant
experience, capture the face, and bring
it back to the golden moon. That's
That's a good technique. That's fine.
It is a loss of the object.
But, it it's fine, because you were
already off.
Okay?
All right, I'm going to do just 5-10
minutes on just for good luck, okay? So,
this is the first day of the year.
It's a good way to go to bed.
I'm I'm trying to take it easy the first
2 days, okay?
And then, we'll
then we'll push. But, uh, so many people
are so exhausted, especially down in
mountain people.
You're You're like
That looks really amazing.
They just burned it really hard for
months and
you know, they're going to get sick and
they're
We need to give them a couple days of
recovery. The China people burned it for
a month and then before that where were
we? I don't remember.
I can't even remember. It's all a blur.
We were somewhere.
It was Germany.
No.
Yeah, it was Puerto Vallarta.
Yeah, okay. All right.
Okay.
We just finished those three different
ways of looking at me, right?
And then we said, "Oh, it's only the
third one
that needs to be smashed."
Okay, which is the
actively believing that you come from
yourself.
D number you victor got to you.
Uh it's the third
it's the third perception of who Michael
is
that is the one which is to be denied or
which is to be canceled or or fought
against.
Which is got cha, right? Got by the way
means stop. Cha means that which is to
be.
Got cha means that which is to be denied
or to stop.
So it's the me it's the me which under
consideration right?
Under active consideration of whether
it's coming from itself or not, I decide
it's coming from
itself. That's got cha. That's the
Michael that doesn't exist. Okay? If you
question me,
does that Michael come from Michael? And
if I say yes, then that Michael is the
gotcha.
Okay? The Michael I'm thinking of then
is is the thing
that doesn't exist and never did exist.
And that's what emptiness is empty of.
Okay? That's gotcha. Third one.
What was the second one? Since you look
so
you look so
Unexamined.
What did you call that? Clueless.
What was the second one?
John Polli.
That is John Polli in the mirror. You
know, you're shaving and you're like,
"Okay, John's there." And you know, you
got to pay attention or you're going to
cut your lip off.
Uh he's there. It's okay. You can shave
his face.
That's John. That's an unexamined
you know, nobody's worried about whether
he's coming from himself or not. You're
just trying not to cut your lip off.
Okay? Then the first one?
That was of a of a a real
sage.
He's looking at their arm and saying,
"You know, it could have been life
if I were just a little more
uh respectful of life.
You see? Could have been life."
And
that's how they perceive Mike. Okay?
All right.
Dring the baby gotcha. Now they
distinguish between gotcha and long
gotcha. Say rigpa gotcha.
Rigpa gotcha.
Long gotcha.
These are there are two kinds of gotcha.
Okay?
One never existed in the first place,
and that's the Mike that's coming from
Mike.
The Mike that's coming from his own
side.
Okay? The Mike who's Mike without me
there
to make it Mike. The pen that's a pen
without me making it a pen.
That's the
that's one kind of gotcha.
Rigpa means it's the kind of
self-existent thing that we deny through
careful thinking.
Careful thinking
overcomes our belief in that mic.
Okay? Careful reflection and instruction
overcomes our tendency to believe in
that mic. Okay? That's the Rippa gotcha.
Lhundrup gotcha means
something which is
uh overcome
through the practice of the lung, which
means what?
Path.
Ever since I went to Australia,
I have to say path.
Right?
Not path.
So,
Lhundrup gotchas, do they exist?
Like anger, desire, jealousy,
hatred.
These exist, okay? They They are
overcome through the practice of the
path.
So, the distinction between the two
gotchas is that the first one that never
existed anyway, and has caused you every
wrinkle on your face,
and all your gray hairs.
They have come
No, really. They have come to uh
being worried about and protecting,
defending a mic that didn't exist in the
first place.
Okay?
That's where I got them. All right?
And all the wrinkles on our face and all
the troubles in your life have come
through defending a mic who was never
there anyway. Slamming the brakes on for
a leaf that is crossing the road, and
smashing your head.
Okay? And then, Lhundrup gotchas,
those exist. Anger, jealousy, desire.
These are
overcome through the path. They are both
things to be overcome. The first one
never was there anyway, which is the big
uh what do you call it? Irony of life.
Your prac-
Ultimately, your practice is aimed at
fighting an enemy who is never there.
Is the belief in the enemy there?
Yeah, and that's a lump of matter.
Okay? That's real.
That exists.
Okay.
But we could debate. That'd be a nice
debate. Nice debate. Okay.
Uh
Shankey key
We're not going to go too long, don't
worry.
And I hate people who really yawn. I'm
just telling you, okay?
Anyway, I had a student who they would
sit in the front right there and they go
ha.
Okay. So, just kind of like
All right.
Uh Shankey key nangso day jesu dung ne
nge se sun nyam pa
ta bo de nga shem pa yin.
This is difficult.
Uh Shankey key nangso means the way Mike
appears to the state of mind you were
born with, right? We talked about what?
Down to
bugs, down to
dreams. That should be a title of a
song, too.
Down to bugs, down to dreams. You got
that?
Down to bugs, down to dreams.
Okay. We're always looking for new songs
for an album.
Uh
The way
Mike appears to the state of mind I was
born with, right?
And then jesu dung means to What do you
call it? There's a word in English. You
fall for it.
Yeah, jesu dung literally means to
follow it.
But in English we say you fall for it,
right? To fall for
the way Mike seems to be to the state of
mind you were born with. Jesu dung ne.
And then nge se sun I ate breakfast.
Okay, yes, yes,
number to
to think that just thinking I ate
breakfast
is to is to grasp on to a mic that's not
there.
That's That's called large large shamba.
Large shamba means
to large shamba means to fall for me.
You know, to fall for a me. To fall for
a me, okay?
Like then you're just to say I ate
breakfast.
Okay?
How often are you wrapped up in the
gutter?
I'll I'll ask you a question. Let's stop
on that, okay? Let's stop right there.
I'll ask you a question.
How many things in the world work? Do
cars work?
A car that works sometimes doesn't work,
okay? In my mind.
You know, give me give me a bottle of a
headache remedy and tell me this is a
headache remedy, but it only works half
the time and then still call it a
headache remedy? No, thanks.
You see? Cuz the times it doesn't work
is so it's so painful.
You see? A car which doesn't work every
time you turn the key, you can't call it
In my mind, you can't call it a car. Try
to get used to that, okay?
You have grown up
in a world You have grown up in a life
where the things around you
don't work.
Because they only work
sometimes.
You don't get on a plane if they tell
you that it's going to fall down half
the time.
That's not a plane.
Okay? You could You want You're going to
fight with me. You're going to say,
"That's a defective plane.
Uh that's a uh lousy plane. That's a
poorly made plane."
Uh I say it's not a plane. Get used to
it, okay? It's just not a plane.
If it doesn't fly you from one place to
another safely,
it's not a plane. It's just a death trap
or something. You see what I mean? It's
an occasional
death trap.
Call it that, but don't call it a plane.
Plane means a functioning thing which
flies you from one city to another
safely.
Okay, that's what a plane is. If it
falls down ever, then it's not a
plane. Just try to struggle with that.
You have
This is where I get into Planet B and
Planet A, okay? There's a whole planet
of people called Planet A.
They live on a planet, 6 billion of
them.
And they put up with this crap.
You know, it's amazing. It's It's It's
unthinkable.
They They will buy a a bottle of pills
knowing that half of them don't work.
And they won't even ask for half their
money back. You know, they'll take that
bottle of aspirin
from the store. They'll pay the full
price. They'll take it home. And if you
ask them to their face, you know, "How
many of these are going to work?"
They'll say, "Half, maybe. I hope."
You know, and and then you're like,
Planet B people are like, "What's wrong
with you? I mean, wake up already."
You know, why Why do you put up with a
world where stuff only works sometimes,
you know?
Like, why
Why do you
go to a job that might work out or might
not work out? You know, why do you buy a
house that might make money or might
lose money? You know, why do you have
Why do you enter a relationship with a
woman or a man and and know that it
might not work out half the time? You
know, what So, why not just enter a
better relationship? Just
What I We On our planet, we wouldn't
even call that a relationship.
If you didn't know that it was going to
work out, we wouldn't call it a
relationship. We'd call it like, I don't
know, gambling
or something. Everything you do is like
gambling here.
Everything you plan is like gambling.
You're really strange people.
You know, and cuz the ironic thing is
you you put up with it.
You know, you don't complain anymore.
It's It's You say it's good enough.
You know, my car starts most days.
That's okay.
And you know, it breaks sometimes, and I
just be grateful with it.
And then religious religiosity to you is
gratefulness in the face of fuck-ups.
You know, uh
You know, the car breaks, and I try to
stay calm, and I'm a good person. You
know, and we're like planet B people are
like, "Why don't you just get a car that
doesn't break, and you don't have to be
a nice person?"
You know,
uh
you know, we don't understand.
How many things in your life don't work?
The water.
Everything. Those are all gotchas. Okay?
Try to grasp that. They're all gotchas.
None of them even exist.
Try to grasp it, okay? They don't even
exist.
If an object in your life only works
sometimes, if a car only works
sometimes, it's not a car.
Okay? Try to get it.
It's so frustrating to come from planet
B and talk to planet A people.
Uh
It's a gotcha. That car is a gotcha.
It's not a car.
That aspirin that you take is not
aspirin. If it doesn't work every time
you take it, it's It's I swear to God
it's not an aspirin.
It's not
Uh
Okay? You can try to I'm just throwing
it out before you I'm trying to put you
to bed with some
in common
that you never seen anything correctly
your whole life.
Okay? Nothing.
Okay?
Cuz they don't work, okay? So,
you You surrounded by gotchas. You are
living in a world of god tests.
You are living in a fantasy world. You
are living in a world of
of holograms or something, you know?
It's all
fake cars and fake
friends and fake relationships and fake
medicines and
and you put up with At least be a little
dissatisfied.
You know? I mean, if someone comes from
another planet and says
it could be different.
Every car you ever bought
could work forever.
without gas.
You know?
No, I mean, if you said 20 years ago
uh you could communicate instantaneously
with everybody on the planet for free.
You'd you'd laugh at the person. You'd
say it's not possible. You would
I I
The internet's a good example of of
potential.
You know? Like, try to grasp
that uh
Okay, I'll tell you This is the last
thing, okay?
The the thing we remember Grant for
before I run into the truth.
I respect you.
Yeah, okay. The big contribution we can
remember something is uh
took class. He's a great student. And he
said a very beautiful thing.
He said, "Guess what? I got to see this
comedy act that is on
Letterman or I don't know the guy's
name. Letterman?"
Yeah, whatever.
Uh
And I said uh You know, people are
constantly send me links to things and I
get CDs all the time. I have a whole
stack of CDs that people thought was
important music.
And I save them and then once a year I
play them.
And I just I have a 10-second test.
Uh I listen to any 10 seconds of it and
if it's not good, I just throw it out,
you know? I listen to the next one. So,
anyway, he sends me a link and I'm like,
"Okay, Grant. Thanks, you know?"
But I actually looked at it. And uh So,
it's this guy is a comedian. He's just
um
And And he's talking to some game show
What do you call it? To night show host.
Talk show host.
And he And the guy says
The comedian is saying I I don't do it
very well, but he's saying uh
Look, you know,
the world's a little special. You know,
the world's
it's a pretty amazing world, you know?
And
like I was on a plane the other day
and I'm sitting next to this guy
and he's he's working on his laptop. And
then the stewardess comes on and says,
"We're proud to announce that American
Airlines is the first airline
to have wireless
in the plane
while you're flying, you know?" So, the
guy's like, "Oh, great, wireless, you
know?"
And he's he's watching the guy next to
him. The guy next to him is all excited.
He's like, "Oh, wireless on a plane,
this is fantastic, you know? I can get
on Facebook, you know?" And he's like,
you know, and he's like he's like
clicking, you know? And then he's like
clicking and then he starts banging on
the keys, you know? And he's like
And then the guy said, "What's wrong?
Isn't it working?" He says, "Yeah, it's
working, but it's slow.
It's slow, you know?" And then the other
guy is like,
"But no other plane ever had internet
ever before. You're on a plane that has
internet for the first time in history.
You have it You have Yeah, but it's
goddamn slow,
you know?
And then the guy says, "Take it easy,
man. Look, that The signal goes to a
satellite, okay? It comes back down to
the airplane from a satellite. You give
it some goddamn time already, you know?
It's a long way to go,
you know? It's got to go up to outer
space, hit this little satellite. How it
hits a little satellite out of the whole
space.
It comes back to this plane.
And you're on Facebook. So, if it's just
a little slow, just deal with it
already. And then And then he says, "And
by the way,
you're flying through the goddamn air
in a chair made of steel.
Iron Iron in an iron chair.
Of all the people who lived on this
planet in history, you are flying
through the air in a chair made of iron.
Like, be a little appreciative.
You know.
It was nice.
But what's it mean for us?
No, it means
big things can happen. Strange, weird
things can happen. Don't think Don't
think there can't be a day when all the
aspects work.
And when a car that doesn't work is
unknown, there's no word for a car
that's broken or a car that doesn't
start.
Like
if we understood
how things work. If the cars are coming
from cars, then okay, you can live on
your planet A and you can live like you
are. Hit or miss.
Gambling and then dying because you
didn't do the gamble right.
You can go on like that. If If things
were coming from themselves
it's it's not so What do you call it?
Tragic.
Uh but they're not.
The things are coming from you.
And And And then to put up with a world
where you get killed at the end and you
lose everything, that's a tragedy.
That's a huge tragedy, you know? And we
don't People on our planet, we're like
you know
try to work it out. Try to understand
emptiness, right?
And then that those Don't tell me things
can't change radically.
You know, don't tell me that
that uh
anybody in the world for free can
contact another person in the world
instantaneously.
Right? In any language. You got Google
Translator?
I have whole conversations with people
from the Ukraine. And it always ends
with I did this on Google Translator.
Please excuse if it's not quite right,
you know? They just type Ukrainian into
Google Translator and they hit a button
and it changes it into this really
interesting English.
No, but we are working. We are We are
We're doing projects together. And you
know, every once in a while there's some
weird sentence, but
but isn't that amazing? Now, if you use
Google Translator,
it doesn't even matter if you don't
speak the person's language. You can
have instant And they have Chinese. You
You can do anything.
So, instantaneous
communication between people of
different languages in any part of the
world
for free.
Yeah.
Yeah, it does. You paste it into the
Google
You cut and paste. 300-word limit, okay?
It's a little cumbersome cumbersome
cumbersome if you're doing an
an encyclopedia or something.
But But don't tell me weird stuff can't
happen, you know, in your lifetime.
In your lifetime. You You must have some
really weird karma because in your
lifetime
it's become This has happened in your
lifetime, okay?
You must be something special.
Cuz Cuz this thing, which never existed
in
in 50,000 years of recorded history, has
happened in in a few years of your life.
So, don't tell me
you can't take it a little further. All
right?
Okay. Have a nice bedtime.
We'll do this more tomorrow. Okay.